In this video, we are going to look at
another synchronization primitive: semaphores.
A semaphore is a special variable/data
object that can be used for signaling.
It is handled via 2 atomic
operations: wait and signal.
If a thread is waiting for a signal, it will
remain blocked until that signal is sent.
We have seen such a behavior in the lecture
about multi-threaded processes and pthreads.
Here we have the description
of how signal and wait work.
When invoking signal on variable S,
the variable is atomically incremented.
When invoking wait on S, the thread
invoking the function will loop or
remain blocked until S value is 0. After that,
it will exit after decreasing the value of S.
S can take only values 0 and
1 if it is a binary semaphore
or also greater than one if
it is a counting semaphore.
At this point, you can hopefully see semaphores
can be used as shown in this pseudocode to
handle the critical section problem (but
please try to reason formally by yourself!)
Something worth noticing about semaphores
is that they can be used to create an order
in the execution of two threads. If we
want to execute code segment opB from TB
only after code segment opA has been executed
in Ta, we can do it as shown in the slide. Since
B waits for a signal from A, and A sends a signal
after opA, then opB will be executed after opA.